So, I want to start by saying that I'd
like to talk to you about ethics and
intelligence operations or even the the
lack of ethics and intelligence
operations. I was very fortunate to have
spent 15 years at the CIA and the second
half of my career was in
counter-terrorism operations. Very
tough,
but fun. The most fun I ever had in my
life. Went to 65 countries, really felt
like I was making an impact for the for
the United States. Uh September 11th
changed all that. It became deadly
serious on September 11th and was
frankly a lot less fun. But like
everybody else in the building on
September 11th, I volunteered repeatedly
to go to Afghanistan to fight or do
whatever was required of me. And finally
I was sent to Pakistan as the chief of
CIA counter-terrorism operations there.
About 6 weeks after I arrived, we got
word from CIA headquarters that Abu
Zubaydah was somewhere in Pakistan and
we had to catch him.
We thought at the time that Abu Zubaydah
was the number three in Al-Qaeda. He was
a very big fish.
Well, Pakistan is the size of Texas and
it has almost 200 million people in it.
So, to say he's somewhere in Pakistan,
go catch him, it's total non-starter.
I came up with a couple of really bad
ideas. They resulted in nothing. It was
a waste of time. And finally I told CIA
headquarters I needed a targeting
analyst. A targeting analyst is someone
who pours through vast amounts of data
and is able to pinpoint the location of
a target. And so a targeting analyst
came, worked for another 2 weeks, and
finally told me that he just simply
could not pinpoint Abu Zubaydah's
location to fewer than 14 sites.
We had never hit more than two sites in
one night before. And so I asked
headquarters to send a large team. We
ended up flying in three dozen
people, half CIA, half FBI. We paired
them with Pakistani military officers.
And on the night of March 22nd, 2002, we
broke down the doors of 14 safe houses
simultaneously.
I'm not allowed to say how many people
we caught that night, but I can tell you
it was many dozens of Al-Qaeda fighters.
He was shot three times while trying to
escape. A Pakistani policeman shot him
in the thigh, the groin, and the
stomach. And we rushed him to a hospital
in Faisalabad to try to save him. But
word had gotten around the Al-Qaeda
community that we had gotten him. And so
Al-Qaeda fighters began driving by the
hospital and just opening fire on the
hospital. I said to my Pakistani
colleague, "If they realize that we're
unarmed, we're dead. Can you get a
helicopter in here?" 20 minutes later a
helicopter landed. We loaded him onto
the helicopter and we flew to a
Pakistani military base. He was
unconscious for another 24 hours. But my
instructions that came directly from the
director of the CIA, George Tenet, were
24/7 CIA eyes on. I was not to leave his
bedside. And so I tore up a sheet and I
tied him to the bed because I was afraid
frankly that that was going to fall
asleep and he was going to escape.
Uh he was really in no condition to
escape. He was tied like this and he had
an oxygen mask on. And finally he woke
up after 24 hours and he motioned for me
to come over to his bedside. And I moved
his oxygen mask and I said to him in
Arabic, "What is your name? Shu ismak?"
And he shook his head. And I repeated
it, "Shu ismak?" And he said to me in
English, "I will not speak to you in
God's language." I said, "That's okay,
Abu Zubaydah. We know who you are."
He said, "Please, brother, kill me. Take
the pillow and kill me." And I said,
"Nobody's going to kill you. We've been
looking for you for a long time."
I said, "You're going to get the best
medical care that the American
government can provide, but I'm going to
give you a piece of advice.
I am the nicest guy that you're going to
meet in this experience.
My colleagues,
they're not as nice as I am.
So, if there's one thing that you do,
it's that you have to cooperate."
And he said, "You seem like a nice man,
but you're the enemy and I'll never
cooperate."
I said, "Suit yourself."
Another 24 hours later a private jet
flew in.
Three FBI agents and I loaded him onto
the plane. We strapped his gurney down
on the luggage rack in the back.
And I whispered to him, "Remember, you
have to cooperate." And the plane took
off. I never saw him again. 2 months
later I was back at CIA headquarters.
I was in the cafeteria getting lunch and
a senior officer in the
counter-terrorism center approached me
and said, "Hey, I'm glad I ran into you.
Uh do you want to be certified in the
use of enhanced interrogation
techniques?"
I had never heard that that term before.
And so I asked him what he meant. And he
explained what these 10 different
techniques were. And I said, "Man, that
sounds like a torture program. Are you
crazy?"
And he said, "Well, it's not torture
because we had it approved by the White
House." I said, "I I'm not interested.
What's the matter with you people?" I
said, "It's illegal. It's immoral. It's
unethical. Count me out." I'm sorry to
tell you that of the 14 people that they
approached, that I was the only one who
said no.
Uh and that's a very sad thing when you
think about it. So, that was in May of
2002. On the 1st of August 2002, Abu
Zubaydah was tortured.
Uh
waterboarding was supposed to be the
ultimate punishment as part of this
torture program. In fact, the CIA
started by waterboarding him. And he
water he was waterboarded 83 times and
never gave any actionable intelligence
that saved American lives. The
waterboarding was a complete failure.
Well, I left the CIA 2 years later and I
kept my mouth shut. I kept it shut until
December of 2007.
And finally I decided because President
Bush kept saying over and over again,
"There is no torture. There is no
torture. There is no torture." I knew
that was a lie.
And so I went on ABC News and I said
three things. I said, "The CIA is
torturing its prisoners." I said that
torture is official US government
policy. It is not the result of a rogue
as the president had been saying. And
finally I said that the torture program
had been personally approved by the
president himself.
As you can imagine,
the FBI began investigating me like 5
seconds later.
They investigated me for a year from
December of 2007 until December of 2008
and
in December of 2008 they determined that
I had not committed a crime.
What I didn't know was that 3 weeks
later when Barack Obama was inaugurated,
the CIA asked him to secretly reopen the
case against me.
And so for the next 3 years I had no
idea that my emails were being
intercepted, my phone calls were being
intercepted, and that there were three
different FBI surveillance teams
following me all the time.
And in January of 2012, I was finally
charged with five felonies including
three counts of espionage.
Now, espionage is a death penalty case.
And I hadn't committed espionage. You
know, talking to ABC News and the New
York Times is not espionage especially
when you're exposing a crime.
But I was charged with these crimes and
was facing 45 years in prison. To make a
long story short,
it becomes an economic decision. I had
five kids at home.
I had a $1.1 million legal bill.
And the government came back and said,
"Take 30 months and the whole thing goes
away."
Like I said, it's an economic decision.
So, I took the 30 months and I went to
prison.
By the time I got home, the Senate
torture report had been released and it
proved that everything I said was true.
And then in the summer of 2015 when
Congress passed the McCain-Feinstein
Amendment, which formally and
permanently banned torture,
Senator John McCain said that my
revelations were the inspiration for
that law. So, 23 months in prison,
it was worth it because torture is
finally illegal in this country. Now,
that's a uh
Thank you.
I
I never thought I remember because we
already had the the Federal Torture Act
of 1946 and we had the United Nations
Convention Against Torture, which was
ratified by the Senate and has the force
of law.
Uh and I I asked rhetorically,
"Why in 1946
did we execute Japanese soldiers who had
waterboarded American prisoners of war?"
It was a death penalty offense to
waterboard someone in 1946. In January
of 1968, the Washington Post ran a front
page photograph of an American soldier
waterboarding a North Vietnamese
prisoner.
On the day that that photo was
published, the Secretary of Defense,
Robert McNamara, ordered an
investigation. That soldier was
arrested. He was charged with torture.
He was convicted and sentenced to 20
years in a military prison.
So, why was torture illegal in 1946 and
illegal in 1968, but somehow magically
legal in 2002?
The law never changed. We changed.
So, what can we do to make sure that
this doesn't happen again? I can stand
here and tell you we need to write and
blog and speak and protest and blah blah
blah. None of that works. It makes us
feel better, but it doesn't work.
What we have to do
is two things. We have to ride our
elected officials to make sure that they
do what we tell them to do. And if they
don't, we vote them out of office. And
we have to be staunch about it.
The second thing
The second thing is I'm a realist. I
know that the CIA is not going away.
It's not going to be broken up and
scattered to the wind like John Kennedy
wanted to do. It's here to stay. So,
what happens?
Young people like you join the CIA.
Change it from the inside.
Once you've been in there 10 years,
you're going to be surprised because
you're going to be in a position of
authority and you can change it and then
it'll stay changed. So, thanks for
listening to me.
Very best of luck.
Thank you.